We've established that the marketing landscape is complex.
从前面几个视频可以得出 市场营销领域是非常复杂的
We have data being collected and delivered through a vast ecosystem of platform.
有一个庞大的平台体系在收集、分析数据
We can combine this data layering it and segmenting it to answer our key questions.
我们可以整合这些数据 多角度多层次地分析 从而回答某些关键问题
Additionally, we have a process by which we can look at the analytics,
另外 分析也有一套流程
and we even have a methodology by how we analyze these insights.
甚至如何分析洞察 都有自己的一套方法论
Now, we're always looking to capture the right data based on
我们的目的永远是根据目标
our objectives and figuring out
来抓取正确的数据 然后做出恰当的数据分析
the insights that we specifically need to get out of this data.
得出正确的数据洞察
But when it comes time to actually start pulling these metrics,
抓取数据或者确认指标的时候
it can be confusing to know how much data you need to answer your question.
到底要抓取多少数据才能够回答问题呢？这就有点难了
So I encourage you to approach
所以 我希望你可以尽可能开展不同的分析项目
every analytics project so that you can answer these five questions.
然后练习回答以下五个问题
First, what happened?
第一个：发生了什么？
Are we looking at a data point or multiple data points.
我们是仅仅看当前的数据点还是多个数据点？
We're usually looking at this data in comparison to something.
我们通常会将当前数据与历史数据进行比较
So oftentimes, we'll see that the trend is up or a trend is down,
然后比较的时候 就会发现一个上升或者下降的趋势
and that'll indicate that something has happened.
这就说明有什么事情发生了 导致这个趋势
Then we need to ask ourselves,
然后 我们需要问
are these results good?
这些数据/结果/变化是好的吗？
Now we talked a little about how we evaluate this,
刚才 我们有提及如何评估一个变化
change and context help us understand if this is normal or abnormal.
应该与历史数据比较 同时结合背景 来判断变化是否正常
Once we've identified that,
一旦确认了第二个问题的答案
we need to understand why did it happen,
我们需要了解为什么会发生这个变化
and this is where it gets really complex.
这就很复杂了
Now we're being a detective.
需要我们仔细探究
There are many ways that can contribute to why something happened.
某个变化的发生有很多原因
Lots of data to discover,
需要非常多的数据支持
to figure out what went wrong or what went right.
才能综合判断出到底是哪里导致了这个变化
It's also important that we be careful between causation and correlation because
同时 我们要警惕区分 因果关系与关联关系
oftentimes we can compare the wrong data
比如 如果我们对比了错误的数据
or the right data and get drastically different answers.
而不是正确的数据 结论就完全不一样了
Next, we need to figure out what's happening now.
接下来 我们要了解当前的情况是怎样的
Right, we want to figure out if this trend is continuing or if
这个趋势还在继续？
this event happened one time or if it's going to keep happening.
还是偶发性事件？ 或者 它会重复发生？
Finally, what will happen in the future.
最后 我们要考虑以后会怎样
Remember, we're always thinking about actionability.
记得吗 我说过应该时刻考虑执行方案
So what's going to happen if we don't change
比如 如果不做任何改变 会发生什么？
things or what will happen if we change things.
如果做出某些改变 会发生什么？
Again, some things are going to be one time occurrences.
像我刚才说的 有些变化是偶发性的
Other events might be the start of growth or decline.
而有些事件则是增长或者消退的开始迹象
Now, when we think about the future,
那么接下来呢？
we can start forecasting by manipulating the data.
我们可以通过数据分析来做未来预期
Let's think about this a different way.
来举个例子
Say you're asked to review
比如 你需要评估你的网店
the sales performance of your e-commerce store from last Friday.
在上星期五的销量表现
So what happened? Let's say we had 30 sales.
假设我们卖出了 30 单
Okay. Are these results good?
30 个订单是好的成绩吗？
Well, we need to figure out if this particular measurement is good or bad,
想要知道这个结果是好或坏
which means we have to compare it.
我们首先来进行比较
So we'll use that historical dataset or even benchmarks that already
我们可以用相应的历史数据 如果有现成的销量基准 也可以用来比较
exist to determine whether what we have is good or bad.
从而决定这个结果是好还是不好
Again, I like to use the change and contexts within that select time period.
同时 我们也需要考虑到所选时间段是否有任何特殊背景或者变化
So let's say we look at change.
我们先假设变化
We identify that this is a 50 percent lift from last Friday.
假设 今天业绩与上周五相比上升了 50%
What's the context then,
上升的背景是什么？
is this normal or abnormal?
50% 是好还是不好？
Well, we have to think about this.
我们来思考一下
It could be good or it could be bad.
可以是好 也可以是不好
Is there seasonality involved?
比如 可以思考下是否有节假日的原因
Let's say today is a holiday.
比如 今天是个假期
So a 50 percent lift from last Friday can actually be
那么 50% 上升实际上可能是个很差的销量表现
bad if we should have expected 150 percent lift.
因为我们可能预期的是 150% 上涨幅度
So now we need to figure out why it happened.
我们需要搞清楚什么导致了这个变化
Let's say it ends up being a good thing.
假设 我们发现这个变化是好的
Are we running a promotion?
那么 是因为我们最近做的促销活动吗？
Is that promotion what contributed,
是促销活动起的作用吗？
or did more traffic come to the site?
有更多的顾客浏览了我们的网店吗？
Was there a blog mentioned somewhere on the web?
还是网上有博客推荐了我们的网店？
You have to connect all the dots.
这些都需要考虑到
We need to identify where this lift came from because that
我们需要搞清楚是什么导致了变化
will help us figure out later what we do when we forecast into the future.
这样会有助于我们后续做未来预测
So what's happening right now?
那么
Well, we look at this and we say sales are still up,
我们可以得出类似结论 比如销量趋势是上升的
and relative to what we typically see.
与通常预期相似
By knowing that what's happening now follows a positive trend,
知道目前的情况是处于上升的趋势 而不是下降的趋势中
we're less concerned than if it was following a negative trend.
我们才能心安
Finally, what might happen in the future.
最后 要思考未来会发生什么
Well now, we can start to understand if we expect this pattern to continue or not.
比如 可以首先考虑下我们是否希望这个趋势继续下去
If it was seasonality,
如果是节假性或者季节性的
then we know that this is going to drop off.
那我们知道过了节假日 销量肯定会下降的
If it was a new marketing promotion,
如果是因为促销活动
then we might think, well,
那么我们可能会得出类似结论：
if we keep investing this spend,
如果继续花钱做类似的促销活动
then we should keep getting these results.
销量可能会一直上升
Now you can plug that data in and start asking great questions.
我们可以根据数据 继续问一些更实际的问题
If we keep spending this much money,
如果继续投资花钱做促销
are we going to keep getting this return,
我们的回报能保持当前的趋势吗？
and if so, what does that mean for our bottom line?
如果是的话 我们的底线在哪里？
Can we spend more money and create more revenue.
我们可以花了更多钱 从而得到更高的营业收入吗？
In which case, you start to get into forecasting and projecting,
这个时候 就涉及预期与预测了
and now you start thinking about how you can build actionable insights.
这个时候我们可以开始考虑如何根据洞察 做出一个可执行的方案
Now we can take action.
然后就可以行动了
We can say, well, we're going to forecast,
如果预测的话
and now we start thinking about hypotheses and testing,
就会涉及到假设与验证 00:04:52,595 --&gt; 00:00:00,000 在后续课程里会讨论这些